Guide to the Colonial and Early American Papers, 1739-1910 M0018
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Colonial and Early American Papers,
1739-1910
M0018
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
1.0 Linear feet
Boutwell, George Sewall
Bull, Roger
Burr, Aaron
Clay, Henry
Grotjan, P. A.
Jackson, Andrew
Jefferson, Thomas
Kirkland, Samuel
Marquand, John Guerin
Newton, Noah
Pringle, Robert
Roseboom family
Rush, Benjamin
Shreve, Israel
Thornton, Thomas
Washington, George
Webster, Daniel
Wolcott, Roger
Scope and Contents Note
This collection includes correspondence, diaries, account books, financial, legal and land papers, clippings, and other papers relating to the Revolutionary War, the War of 1812, the Mexican War, and life in early America.
Provenance:
Information on provenance of the individual series, when known, is included in the container list.
Access Restrictions:
None.
- Series M0018a New York Manuscripts, 1739 -1910
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains correspondence and financial documents concerning purchase and/or transfer of property by members of the Roseboom family and a Benoni Rose near Cherry Valley (near Albany), New York.
  Custodial History note
  Gift of Mary E. Stewart, 1961
  - Correspondence, 1760-1859 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - James Syme to Barent [Barent] Roseboom, [1760] June 26
    - Joseph Scott, Jr., to Myndert Roseboom, 1771 Aug. 31
    - Barent Roseboom to "Brothers,", 1804 July 14
    - Abraham Van Vechten to Barent Roseboom, [1805] June 16
    - Daniel Hale to Barent Roseboom, 1805 Aug. 24
    - Abraham Van Vechten to A. Roseboom, 1806 Aug. 25
    - Abraham Van Vechten to Coenradt Gansvoort, 1807 Aug. 21
    - Abraham Van Vechten to C. Gansvoort, 1807 Dec. 23
    - Abraham Roseboom to A. Van Vechten, 1808 July 30
    - Abraham Van Vechten to A. Roseboom, 1808 Sept. 20
    - Abraham Van Vechten to A. Roseboom, 1809 Apr. 3
    - Abraham Van Vechten to A. Roseboom, 1809 May 16
    - Abraham Van Vechten to A. Roseboom, 1810 Oct. 31
    - [N. C. Waddell?] to Benoni Rose, 1845 July 25
    - Chauncey Beadle to Mrs. Maria Rose, 1847 July 26
    - H. Lathrop to [Mrs. Maria Rose], [1847] Oct. 9
    - Thomas H. Betts to [Mrs. Maria Rose], 1850 Sept. 2
    - [S. D. Jacobs] to Henry Roseboom, 1851 Dec. 17
    - W. Lochead to [Maria] Rose, 1859 May 12
    - D. H. Little to Benoni Rose, n.d.
  - Financial (bonds, accounts, price lists, I.O.U.'s, promissory notes, bank drafts, checks, bills, receipts, mortgages and abstracts of), 1768-1799 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial (bonds, accounts, price lists, I.O.U.'s, promissory notes, bank drafts, checks, bills, receipts, mortgages and abstracts of), 1801-1874 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Legal (indentures, deeds, agreements, leases), 1760-1799 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Legal (indentures, deeds, agreements, leases), 1800-1891 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (plats, land descriptions, diploma, law license, photo reprint, coat of arms) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ancestry and Descendents of John Roseboom and Jesse Johnson (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ancestral Tablets. Bound volume of handwritten geneological tables (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Oversize documents
    - Deed from George II of Great Britain to John Lindesay, with heavy wax seal of colony of New York, 1739 May 12
    - Appointment of Myndert Roseboom as Lt. Colonel. Signed by Cadwallader Colden, 1762 Mar. 20
    - Indenture between "John Cruger, Philip Livingston, Leonard Lispenard, Henry Holland and William Bayard of the City of New York, trustees of the estate of Abraham De Peyster, late treasurer of the Colony of New York.. .", 1771 May 15
    - Nursing diploma from St. Luke's Hosptial, Catherine Augusta Roseboom, 1909 May 20
    - Minnesota State Board of Examiners of Nurses, "Registered Nurse," Catherine Augusta Roseboom, 1910 Oct. 28
- Series M0018b Massachusetts Documents, 1741-1761
  - Deed for land on Nantucket Island; and four appointments of Stephen Greenleaf as justice and sheriff of Suffolk Co., Mass.
- Series M0018c Roger Wolcott Journal
  This series contains a copy, made in 1820 from the original in the Connecticutt Historical Society, of Wolcott's journal of the 1745 military expedition against Louisburg, Cape Breton Island, Canada, which also includes other writings. The series also includes two original letters, 1759 and 1820.
  Purchased from Holmes Book Co., 1930
  - Wolcott journal and letters, 1745-1820 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series M018d State of Franklin Documents
  Gift of Mrs. S. N. Partridge, 1961
  - Warrants, indictments, and other items from the State of Franklin, Greene County, 1780-1794 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series M018e Israel Shreve Diary, 1775-1776
  On deposit from John L. Strangman, 1964
  - Diary fragment describing journey from New Jersey to Chamble and Quebec, Canada (campaign of Generals Arnold, Thomas, and Schuyler), 1775 Nov. 8 -1776 Nov. 22 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series M018f George Washington Documents, 1775-1799
  This series consists of one draft (money), a possible forgery, two facsimile letters, and a facsimile of accounts with U. S., 1775-1783, made by Treasury Dept. in 1833.
  - George Washington documents, 1775-1799 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series M018g Benjamin Franklin Letter, 1775
  - Facsimile of letter, 1775 July 5 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series M018h Robert Pringle Papers, 1767
  This series consists of two documents signed by Robert Pringle, notary of Berkley County, South Carolina -list of stolen goods and sworn statement of Robert Man, eye witness, 1767 Feb. 25,and sworn statement of Thomas Govin of suit brought against William Browning, 1767 Apr. 10-and a clipping.
  Gift of Miss. Clair MacDonald
  - Pringle, Robert, documents, 1767 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series M018i Dr. Benjamin Rush Papers, 1775-1803
  Gift of Ray Lyman Wilbur, 1943.
  - Bills and receipts for medical service and order on bank by Samuel Coates to pay Rush, 1775-1803 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series M018j Roger Bull Diary, 1776
  On loan from Acton M. Cleveland.
  - Diary of American Forces in New England (area of New Haven and North River). (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series M018k Rev. Williams Papers, 1772-1820
  Gift of Watson Nickolson, 1947
  - Manuscript sermon first preached in 1772 and used until 1820; with accompanying letter from Watson Nicholson, 1947. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series M018l Samuel Kirkland Document, 1789
  - Land grant by State of New York to Kirkland for 2, 840 acres in Montgomery Cunty, 1879 Feb. 25. (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series M018m Aaron Burr Papers, 1802-1803
  Gift of John H. Blackburn from the estate of Helen V. Wheeler, 1953.
  - Letter to Burr from P. A. Grotjan re aid to an unfortunate, and letter from Burr to Grotjan, 1802 Dec. 27, 1803 July 22. (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Series M018n Thomas Thornton Papers, 1813 and n.d.
  Gift of J. P. McNeill, 1944.
  - ALS to Patrick [Kain] from U.S. Constellation off Norfolk, VA, during the War of 1812, and a poem [by Mrs. Bewning (?)] on the death of [Mrs. Eleanor de Krafft], n.d., 1813 Mar. 25 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Series M018o John Guerin Marquand Papers, ca. 1822
  - School copy book on "division of vulgar fractions"; the book was written in Baltimore and the name of Elias Marquand also appears. (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Series M018p Henry Clay Letter, 1851
  Gift of Dr. and Mrs. Conrad Weil.
  - ALS, regret to invitation of Burns Club, 1851 Jan. 14 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Series M018q Daniel Webster Letter, 1851
  - ALS regret to invitation of Burns Club, 1851 Jan. 14 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Series M018r George Sewall Boutwell Document, 1852
  - "Passport" to Samuel S. Thorndike, also signed by Amasa Walker, secretary of Commonwealth of Mass., 1852 Jan. 1 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Series M018s Lancashire Fusiliers
  Gift of David D. Barrett, 1956.
  - Letter from [W.] Hill of the Lancashire Fusiliers (in Tientsin, China) to David D. Barrett, with excerpt from the Regimental History of the Fusiliers regarding the American Revolutionary War., 1938 Oct. 2 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Series M018t Miscellaneous Documents, 1777-1833
  - Map by L. Flury of the seige of Ft. Schuyler, N. Y., and facsimile letters of Thomas Jefferson, and Andrew Jackson, n.d.; 1824, 1833. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Reprint of letter from Brig. Gen. Lachlan McIntosh to Col. John Lawrence, regarding the duel between McIntosh and Button Gwinnett in which Gwinnett died. Reprint by the Amican Autograph Shop, 1777 May 30, 1937. (Box 2, Folder 28a)
- Series M018u Mexican War Collection, 1846-1848
  Newton diary gift of Edith W. Newton, 1958; Doggett letter gift of Mrs. Robert L. Duffus, 1974.
  - "Uncle Noah's Mexican War Diary; being an account of the personal experiences and comments of Captain Noah Newton, U.S.A., Regiment of Mounted Rifles." Prepared for publication by George C. Newton, also includes hand-drawn copies of some of the original illustrations in the diary., [1846 June 6 -1848 Aug.] [ca. 1932] (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - ALS from Samuel [Doggett] to his father [John Doggett] re the war with Mexico, 1847 Mar. 28 (Box 2, Folder 29a)
- Series M018v Colonial and Revolutionary Facsimiles, 1775-1791
  - Six manuscripts and a map regarding the battles of Lexington and Concord, Declaration of Independence, Constitution of the United States, Bill of Rights, and a letter from Benjamin Franklin to Samuel Cooper, 1775; 1776; 1787; 1791; 1778 Feb. 27. (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Series M018w Noah Welles Sermon, 1764
  Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Francis Sumner, 1964.
  - Sermon by Rev. Noah Welles dated and given by him until 1772., 1764 Dec. 22 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Series M018x The True Story of the Romance of Nathan Hale and Alice Adams, 1926-1929
  Gift of Mary E. Hastings.
  - Letters from Mary E. Hastings to Ray Lyman Wilbur, booklet, and clipping concerning the romance of Nathan Hale with Alice Adams, Hasting's great-grandmother. (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Series M018y Land Indenture, 1811
  - Land indenture signed by Lawrence and Maria Vrooman in Neskayuna, Schenectady County, New York, 1811 Sept. 23. (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Series M018z Early Slavery Documents, 1807-1858
  - Thomas Wright to Capt. Rich, about selling a slave, 1807 June 29. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Jn. Taylor Somac to Major George Lewis, about slavery and Dangerfield, 1812 Feb. 16. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Inventory and appraisement of the estate of James Stephens, dec'd, ten slaves listed as part of the property., 1831 Feb. 21 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Martin Z. Tupper to Dear Sir, about slavery, 1858 Oct. 7. (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Series M018aa David Crockett Documents, n.d.
  Gift of Ethel M. Day, 1970.
  - Contemporary holograph copy of David Crocket poem "Farewell to the Mountains;" verifax copy of a Crockett letter; page from Story of the Wild West by William Cody containing the poem and an illustration; and biographical information on Crockett. (Box 2, Folder 35)